Society of Indian Psychologists; Records apap390
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Society of Indian Psychologists Records
2015-2020
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
apap390
176 Digital Files
This collections documents the operations of the Society of Indian Psychologists.
Content Description
This collection includes hundreds of digital files created by Society of Indian Psychologists' leadership in recent years. Materials include administrative records, newsletters, subject files, and correspondence.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is unprocessed and is likely disorganized. Individual items may be difficult to find.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Past President Gayle Morse, PhD (Mohawk) donated all materials to the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives in March 2021.
Access
Access to this collection is restricted because it is unprocessed. Portions of the collection may contain recent administrative records and/or personally identifiable information. Please contact an archivist for more information.
Historical Note
The Society of Indian Psychologists (SIP) is an organization for Native American Indigenous people who advocate for the mental well-being of Native peoples by increasing the knowledge and awareness of issues having an impact upon Native mental health.
Per SIP's By-laws' the term "Indian" refers to the Indigenous people of the Americas. Individual members of SIP who are Indigenous usually prefer to be identified by their traditional tribal names. Other group names sometimes referred to are Indigenous, Alaska Native, American Indian, Native American, Native Hawaiian, First Nations, Aboriginal people, and Native people.
Arrangement
In respect of the organization's records keeping structure, the series has been arranged chronologically. Series typically consist of documents pertaining to the Annual Convention of American Indian Psychologists, meeting agendas and minutes, articles the organization has written regarding current events, and membership correspondence.
Recent phone numbers have been struck from documents in an effort to protect the privacy of the Society of Indian Psychologists' members.
Indians of North America--Psychology; Medicine and Health Care
- Records from President Jacqueline Gray (Term: 2012-2014)
  - Records for 1976-1999
    - Network of Indian Psychologists (NIP) Newsletter #7, 1976 March
    - Network of Indian Psychologists (NIP) Newsletter #11, 1977 March
    - Network of Indian Psychologists (NIP) Newsletter #12, 1977 July
    - Network of Indian Psychologists (NIP) Newsletter Summer, 1978
    - 21st Annual Convention of American Indian Psychologists and Psychology Graduate Students Training Module #1, 1978
    - SIP Group Photo at APA, with names, 1984
    - SIP Group Photo at APA, 1984
    - USU Conference Photo, with names, 1987
    - USU Conference Photo, 1987
    - SIP Newsletter, Volume 1, No. 1, 1988
    - SIP Newsletter, Volume 1, No. 2, 1988
    - SIP Newsletter Fall, Volume 1, No. 3, 1988
    - SIP Newsletter Spring, Volume 2, No. 1, 1989
    - SIP Newsletter Summer, Volume 2, No. 3, 1990
    - Keeper of the Fire, A Profile of Carolyn Attneave, 1990
    - SIP Newsletter Summer, Volume 2, No. 5, 1991
    - SIP Newsletter Winter, Volume 2, No. 4, 1991
    - SIP Membership List, 1991
    - SIP Newsletter Summer, Volume 3, No. 2, 1992
    - SIP Newsletter Winter, Volume 3, No. 1, 1992
    - Defining SIP Membership, 1993
    - SIP Newsletter Fall, Volume 4, No. 2, 1994
    - SIP Newsletter Fall, Volume 5, No. 2, 1995
    - SIP Newsletter Spring, Volume 5, No.1, 1995
    - SIP Newsletter Spring, Volume 6, No. 1, 1996
    - Obituary of Carolyn Attneave, 1996 May
    - SIP Newsletter Fall, 1999
    - SIP Newsletter Spring, 1999
    - SIP Position on Indian Mascots, 1999
    - SIP Indian Mascot Position Statement, 1999 January 27
    - SIP Indian Mascot Position Statement, with notes, 1999 January 27
  - Records for 2000
    - SIP Newsletter, Spring, 2000
    - SIP Business Meeting Minutes, 2000 June 15
    - SIP 13th Convention Registration Form, Gennea Seibel, 2000 June 15; 2000 June 16
    - SIP 13th Convention Registration Form, Jacque Gray, 2000 June 15; 2000 June 16
  - Records for 2001
    - SIP Newsletter, Fall
    - SIP Meeting Minutes
  - Records for 2002
    - Letter of Mutual Benefit from Jacqueline Gray about Conference Attendance, 2002 May 6
    - SIP Meeting Minutes, 2002 June 24
  - Records for 2003
    - SIP Annual Convention Registration Form (Jacqueline Gray), 2003 June 20; 2003 June 24
    - SIP Meeting Minutes, 2003 June 23
    - SIP Convention Participant List, 2003
  - Records for 2004
    - Convention Participant List, 2004
    - American Indians and Crime, Statistical Report, 2004 December
  - Records for 2005
    - SIP Newsletter, Volume 1, Issue 1, 2005; 2006
    - SIP Conference Participant List, 2005
    - Responsible and Ethical Conduct of Research with Ethnocultural Populations Presentation, 2005
    - Colville Tribal Members' Views of Mental Health and Wellness: A Qualitative Investigation Presentation, 2005
    - Models of Progressive Education and Community Development Presentation, 2005 June 28
  - Records for 2006
    - SIP Agenda, 2006
    - Maze of Injustice: The failure to protect Indigenous women from sexual violence in the USA, Article, 2006
    - Violence Against Native Women: A Guide for Practitoner Action, 2006
    - SIP Meeting Minutes, 2006 June 26
  - Records for 2007
    - Council of National Psychological Associations for the Advancement of Ethnic Minority Interests, Agenda Item, 2007 January 24
    - SIP Business Meeting Minutes, draft, 2007 June
    - SIP Agenda, 2007 June 25
    - SIP Meeting Minutes, 2007 June 25
    - SIP Meeting Agenda, 2007 June 25
    - Convention Participant List, 2007
  - Records for 2008
    - Convention Training Module #1, 2008
    - Convention Training Module #2, 2008
    - Convention Behavioral Health Statistics, 2008
    - Convention Historical Factors of Cultural Disenfranchisement: Reversing the Trend Presentation, 2008
    - Maze of Injustice: The failure to protect Indigenous women from sexual violence in the USA, Article, 2008
    - SIP APA Council of Representatives (CoR) Report, 2008 June
    - SIP Agenda, 2008 June 23
    - Convention Outline, 2008 June 25
    - SIP Agenda, 2008 June 23
    - SIP Meeting Minutes, 2008 June 23
    - Violence Against American Indian and Alaska Native Women and the Criminal Justice Response: What is Known, 2008 August
    - RE: The Diane J. Willis Award for Outstanding Article in the Journal of Pediatric Psychology, 2008 December 10
  - Records for 2009
    - Draft Recommendations Not for Further Distribution Or Citation, 2009
    - An Historical Profile of American Indians and Alaska Natives in Psychology Article, 2009
    - Establishing Local Chapters of the SIP, with annotations, 2009
    - Demographic Characteristics of APA Members by Membership Status, 2009
    - SIP Meeting Agenda, 2009 June 29
    - SIP Minutes, 2009 June 29
    - SIP Executive Committee Meeting Minutes, 2009 June 29
  - Records for 2010
    - Biography of Diane J. Willis, Ph.D., 2010 January 27
    - SIP Newsletter, Winter, 2010
    - Convention Participant List, 2010
    - Grant, Letter of Support, 2010 March 28
    - (Unapproved) Summary Notes of Council of National Psychological Associations for the Advancement of Ethnic Minority Interests (CNPAAEMI) Meeting, 2010 June 20
    - SIP By-laws, 2010 June 28
    - SIP Meeting Minutes, 2010 June 28
    - SIP Chapter Certificate, 2010 July 1
    - SIP Chapter Certificate, Icon, 2010 July 1
    - Demographic Characteristics of APA Members, 2010
  - Records for 2013
    - ACPA Statement of Native American Mascots, 2013 March
    - National Multicultural Conference and Summit - 2013 Elders Nomination Form for Diane Willis
    - SIP President's Report, 2011; 2013
    - FOCUS Newsletter, Fall, Volume 25, No. 1, 2013
    - "On Indian Land, Criminals Can Get Away With Almost Anything", Article, 2013 February 22
    - Policy Insights Brief: Statistics on Violence Against Native Women, 2013 February 6
    - SIP Retreat Agenda, 2013 June 21; 2013 June 23
    - SIP Convention Agenda, 2013 June 24
    - SIP Convention Notes, 2013 June 24
    - Convention Participant List, 2013 July 30
    - APA Communique Newsletter, 2013 September
    - Ending the Legacy of Racism in Sports & the Era Of Harmful "Indian" Sports Mascots Article, 2013 October
    - "So You Call Yourself an Ally: 10 Things All 'Allies' Need to Know" Article, 2013 November 8
  - Records, Undated
    - Background Information Supporting Recommendations for a NAEA Position Statement Regarding the Use of Indian Mascots by non-Native American Schools and Educational Institutions, Undated
    - APA Resolution Recommending the Immediate Retirement of American Indian Mascots, Symbols, Images, and Personalities by Schools, Colleges, Universities, Athletic Teams, and Organizations, Undated
    - Division 45 Distinguished Student Research Award, Undated
    - Division 45 Joseph E. Trimble Award for Distinguished Contributions to Native and Indigenous Psychology, Undated
    - "Insight From My Perspective," Author Unknown, Undated
    - Iva GreyWolf Draft Nomination 2019 National Multicultural Conference and Summit Distinguished Elder, Undated
    - New Fellow Self-Statement from Iva GreyWolf, Ph.D., Undated
    - Teresa LaFromboise - National Multicultural Conference and Summit Distinguished Elder Nominaton Letter, Undated
    - "Missing and Murdered Indigenous Women and Girls in the United States" Article, Undated
    - Missing and Murdered Indigenous Women and Girls in the United States, Report, Undated
    - "American Indian Women Feminism and Leadership Revised II", Article, Undated
    - SIP Affiliation Standards Applicable to Affiliate and Provisional Chapters, Undated
    - SIP Proposal Bylaws Change to Allow for Local SIP Chapters, Undated
    - Sip Minimum Standards for Affiliation, Undated
    - The Implications of the SIP Commentary on the APA Code of Ethics are many, broad and deep., Undated
    - Cultural Humility: Process and content of the SIP Commentary on the APA Code of Ethics, Undated
    - Full Apology to the Native American, Alaska Native, and Native Hawaiian People, drafted by Psychoanalysis for Social Responsibility, Section IX of Division 39 (Psychoanalysis), APA, Undated
    - American Indians and Alaska Natives in Psychology, History Chapter, with Jacqueline Gray edits, Undated
    - Indigenous Women's Leadership, Presentation, Undated
    - SIP Mission Statement Page, with notes, Undated
    - Memorandum of Understanding between the American Psychological Association and the Society of Indian Psychologists, Undated
    - Special Commentary from the SIP, Undated
    - The Memorandum of Understanding, purpose, Undated
    - SIP Membership Information, Undated
    - Mentor-Mentee Evaluation Questions, Undated
    - Domestic Violence Homicide Statistics, Undated
    - Institute for Native Justice Dating Violence Fact Sheet, Undated
    - Institute for Native Justice Sexual Assault Fact Sheet, Undated
    - Institute for Native Justice Stalking Fact Sheet, Undated
    - The Facts on Violence Against American Indian/Alaskan Native Women, Futures Without Violence, Undated
    - Mentor-Mentee Evaluation Questions, with edits, Undated
    - "Injuns Ain't Welcome," Article, Undated
    - 21st Annual Convention of American Indian Psychologists and Psychology Graduate Students- Behavioral Health Statistics Presentation, Undated
    - 21st Annual Convention of American Indian Psychologists & Psychology Graduate Students-Historical Factors of Cultural Disenfranchisement: Reversing the Trend Presentation, Undated
    - 21st Annual Convention of American Indian Psychologists and Psychology Graduate Students Training Module Two: Current Issues in Tribal/Native Behavioral Health, Undated
    - Talking Stick Graphic, Undated
- Records from President Art Blume (Term: 2016-2018)
  - Records for 2016, 2015 September 14 - 2017 September 22
    - Violence Against American Indian and Alaska Native Women and Men, 2010 Findings From the National Intimate Partner and Sexual Violence Survey, 2016 May
    - Emails RE: APA Apology and Catherine Adler, 2013 November 23; 2013 November 24
    - Emails RE: APA Apology, 2013 November 26
    - Action Items from 2015 Conference
    - Letter from SIP Requesting Listing of Representation on COR Website, 2015 September 14
    - Camp Diagram, 2016
    - Major Mental Health Concerns Identified Beyond the Obvious, 2016
    - Psychological First Aid (PFA) Activities for Standing Rock, 2016
    - Psychological First Aid (PFA) Field Operations Guide, 2nd Edition, 2016
    - Standing with Standing Rock Important Info Pack, 2016
    - SIP Provider Training for Standing Rock, 2016
    - Photos of Alliance Notes from SIP, 2016
    - Alliance of National Psychological Associations for Racial and Ethnic Equity, 2016
    - Listserv Research Checklist, 2016
    - Empirical Findings From Psychotherapy Research With Indigenous Populations: A Systematic Review, Article, 2016 October 13
    - Meeting at the Society of Indian Psychologist's Convention, 2016
    - Letter from Principal Investigators, Advocating Against Racism Team, 2016
    - National Ethnic Minority Psychological Associations (NEMPA) Letter, 2016
    - University of Massachusetts Boston Application to the Institutional Review Board (IRB), 2016
    - Research Proposal, 2016
    - SIP- Data Dissemination Plan, 2016
    - SIP Submission Checklist, 2016
    - Listserv Research Checklist, 2016
    - Position Statement Regarding the New Guidelines and Proposed Regulations to the Indian Child Welfare Act (2015), 2016
    - SIP Executive Committee Proposed Agenda, 2016 January 15
    - SIP Executive Committee Proposed Agenda, 2016 February 12
    - Letter RE: Nomination for the Distinguished Career Contribution to Service Award for Daniel V. Foster, PsyD, 2016 February 19
    - Legal Protections for Native Spiritual Practices in Prison, Report, 2016 March
    - SIP Executive Committee Proposed Agenda, 2016 March 25
    - SIP Executive Committee Proposed Agenda, 2016 April 22
    - The APA Ethics Code Through an Indigenous Lens: Introduction to the SIP Commentary on the American Psychological Association's (APA) Ethical Principles of Psychologists and Code of Conduct Presentation, 2017 May 20
    - SIP Executive Committee Proposed Agenda, 2016 June 3
    - SIP Annual Business Meeting Agenda, 2016 June 27
    - Report of the President, Art Blume, 2016 June 27
    - Public Interest Leadership Conference (PILC) Dissemination Awards. V1, 2016 July 26
    - Public Interest Leadership Conference (PILC) Dissemination Awards. V2, 2016 July 26
    - Public Interest Leadership Conference (PILC) Dissemination Awards. V3, 2016 July 26
    - Thank You Letter to Jolleys, 2016 August 7
    - SIP Executive Committee Proposed Agenda, 2016 August 26
    - North American Working Group on Violence Against Indigenous Women and Girls Framing Paper, 2016 September 2
    - PILC Responses, 2016 September 19
    - Budget PI Grant Balance, 2017 September 22
    - SIP Executive Committee Proposed Agenda, 2016 September 30
    - SIP Executive Committee Proposed Agenda, 2016 October 28
    - Journey to Standing Rock, 2016 October 17; 2016 October 19
    - SIP' Response to Pipeline Protest, 2016 October 30
    - SIP Letters to President Obama, 2016 October 27; 2016 November 18; 2016 November 25
    - Standing Rock Letter to President Obama, 2016 November 14
    - List of American Indian/Alaska Native/Native Hawaiin Psychologists, 2016 November 21
    - Missing and Murdered Native Women Public Awareness Efforts, Presentation, 2016 November 30
    - SIP Executive Committee Proposed Agenda, 2016 December 9
    - Letter to Editor of the New York Times, 2016 December 15
    - Public Interest Leadership Conference (PILC) Dissemination Awards. FINAL, 2016
    - Public Interest Leadership Conference Health Equity Dissemination Award Evaluation, 2016
    - Report to Section IX on Presentation of Full Apology Letter to SIP, 2016
    - PRC Tribal Insights Brief, Human & Sex Trafficking, Report, 2016
    - Postt-Standing Rock Re-Integration Handout, 2016
    - Distribution List of Committee Contacts, 2016
    - SIP IM-Intro, Values, Principles. Edits GM, 2016
    - SIP IM-Intro, Values, Principles, 2016
    - Instructor's Manual for the SIP Commentary on the APA Ethics Code Cover Page, 2016
    - Budget PI Grant, 2016
    - Original Budget, 2016
    - SIP Committee Membership Lists, 2017
    - Instructor's Manual for the SIP's Commentary on the American Psychological Association's (APA) Ethical Principles of Psychologists and Code of Conduct, 2017 January 11
    - Research Guidelines for SIP listserv, 2017 March 3
    - Instructor's Manual for the SIP Commentary on the APA Ethics Code with MT edits, 2017 May 11
    - Instructor's Manual for the SIP Commentary on the APA Ethics Code with KJES edits, 2017 May 11
    - SIP Endorsement of Other Organizations Presentation, 2017 May 11
    - APA Ethics Award Committee Nomination Letter for of Melinda Garcia, 2017 May 19
    - Research Project Submission SIP listserv/website, 2017 May 21
    - The Association of Black Psychologists Official Statement RE: Terrorism in Charlottesville, VA, 2017 August 14
  - Records for 2017, 2015 January 20- 2018 August 6
    - Photos of Apology Ceremony, 2017 January 6
    - SIP Executive Committee Proposed Agenda, 2017 January 27
    - SIP Legal Defense Questions and Questions for Dr. Bigfoot, 2017 February 2
    - SIP SR Legal Defense Questions for Dr. Bigfoot, 2017 February 2
    - Executive Council Meeting Minutes, 2017 February 24
    - SIP Executive Committee Proposed Agenda, 2017 February 24
    - Email to UN Special Rapporteur Advocating for Indigenous People, 2017 February 26
    - Letter Nomination RE: Dr. Dolores Subia BigFoot, from Dr. Jacqueline Gray, 2017 March 1
    - SIP Executive Committee Proposed Agenda, 2017 March 24
    - Executive Council Meeting, Special Meeting Minutes to discuss documentary and Water Protectors, 2017 April 21
    - SIP Executive Committee Proposed Agenda, 2017 April 28
    - Letter RE: Dee Bigfoot Nomination for the Joe Trimble Award, from Dianne Willis, 2017 May 1
    - Honoring Missing and Murdered Indigenous Women Webinar, 2017 May 5
    - Letter of Nomination RE: Melinda Garcia, PhD for the Ninth Annual Award for Outstanding Contributions to Ethics Education, from Jacqueline, 2017 May 19
    - SIP Executive Committee Proposed Agenda, 2017 May 26
    - SIP Annual Business Meeting Agenda, 2017 June 26
    - Report of the President, Art Blume, 2017 June 26
    - SIP Financial Report for the Year, 2016 July 1; 2017 June 30
    - SIP Business Meeting Minutes, 2017 June 26
    - SIP Talking Stick, 2017 June 26
    - Hoffman Report, Response and Recommendation, 2015 July 20
    - Looking Back in Our 125th Year: Exploring American Psychology's Past, 2017 August 3; 2017 August 6
    - SIP Executive Council Meeting Minutes, 2017 September 22
    - The SIP Educational Paper Regarding the Use of Counterterrorism Tactics on Native Peoples and Allies, Shortened Version, 2017 October 4
    - The SIP Educational Paper Regarding the Use of Counterterrorism Tactics on Native Peoples and Allies, 2017 October 4
    - Meeting with APA and other EMPA Presidents, 2017 October 7
    - SIP Membership Chair Report, 2017 October 25
    - SIP Executive Council Meeting Minutes, 2017 October 27
    - SIP Executive Council Meeting Minutes, 2017 November 17
    - IVA Survey Draft, 2017 December 8
    - SIP Survey Draft, 2017 December 12
    - SIP Executive Council Meeting Minutes, 2017 December 15
    - SIP Love Surrounds Us, Article, 2017 December 17
    - Representation Agreement, 2017 July 26
    - Amicus Brief Draft, 2017 August 22
    - Amicus Brief, 2017 September 1
    - Letter Nomination RE: Art Blume Fullbright U.S. Scholar Program Selection, from Dr. Jacqueline Gray, 2017 July 10
    - Letter Nomination RE: Art Blume, Joseph E. Trimble Award for Distinguished Contributions to Native and Indigenous Psychology Senior Scholar, 2017 February 28
    - Letter of Recommendation RE: Dan Foster for the Committee on Rural Health CRH, from Jacqueline Gray, 2017 March 16
    - Letter from Finnish Psychologist, Irma Heiskanen, 2017
    - The SIP Statement on the Proposal to Build a Wall between what is Known as the US and what is Known as Mxico, 2017 January 27
    - Group Photo, postikortti, 2017
    - Continuing Education Sponsor Award, final, 2017
    - Letter RE: Ethnic Minority Psychological Associations to the APA, 2017
    - SIP Letter Opposing the Dakota Access Pipeline, 2017
    - Sip Listserv Policies & Procedures, 2017
    - SIP Officers, 2017
    - SIP Survey, Summary, Open Ended Questions, 2017
    - Goals for SIP Organizing Document, 2017
    - Goals for SIP, 2017
    - SIP Survey, 2017-2018
    - SIP Survey Responses, 2017-2018
    - Group Photo, 2017
    - SIP Recommendations for Keystone Pipeline Planning, 2017
    - SIP Presidential Activities, 2017
    - SIP ListSERV Policies and Procedures, 2017
    - SIP Statement Against Counterterrorism Tactics Used Against Water Protectors, 2017
    - Statement Opposing Bans against the People of Seven Nations Entering the US, 2017
    - APA Division 45 Call for Award Nominations, 2017
    - National Multicultural Conference and Summit Elders List, 1999; 2017
    - SIP Mentorship Match Directory, 2017; 2018
    - SIP Mentorship Program Handbook, 2017; 2018
    - SIP 2017 Overview of Tribal Access Program (TAP) for National Crime Information General Executive Brief
    - SIP The Talking Stick Article, 2017
    - Midwinter Meeting Email Draft, 2018 January 19
    - SIP Letter to Council RE NBI 35B and 13D, 2018 August 6
  - Records for 2020, 2019-11 - 2020
    - SIP Executive Committee Meeting Minutes, 2020 January 10
    - SIP Statement RE: an Immediate Halt to the Sharing of Psychotherapy Notes with the United State Immigration and Customs Enforcement Agency, 2020 February 18
    - SIP Mid-Winter Meeting MInutes, 2020 February 21
    - Smoke Signals, Newsletter, 2020 May
    - SIP Statement of Solidarity and Unity with the Black Community, 2020 June
    - SIP Bylaw Final, Rewrite, 2018 June 25
    - What is Elder Abuse and How Do We Prevent It, Notes, 2020 July 27
    - Smoke Signals, Newsletter, 2020 August
    - List of Presidents of the SIP from 1975- 2024, 2020 August 20
    - Smoke Signals, Newsletter, New Year, 2020 January; 2019 November
    - SIP Stephen C. Rose Scholarship for Psychology Research on American Indian, Alaska Native, and Native Hawaiian Youth Application, 2020
    - Descirption of Officer Duties for Upcoming Elections, 2020
    - SIP Election Roster, 2020
    - SIP Vote Tally, 2020
    - Protecting and Defending Our People: Nakni tushka Anowa (A Warrior's Path) Report, 2020
    - List of Presidents of the SIP from 1975- 2020
- Records from President Gayle S. Morse (Term: 2018-2020)
  - Records for 2011, 1999-2011
    - Convention Participant List, 2011
    - Elder Award Previous Winners, 1999; 2011
    - "In a Good Way" A Offiical Publication of The Society of Indian Psychologists, 2011
    - SIP Conference Map, 2011
    - Memorandum of Understanding between the American Psychological Association and the Society of Indian Psychologists, 2011
    - Letter, Supporting Diane Wilis, 2011
    - SIP Newsletter, Spring, 2011
    - Dee BigFoot Elder Recognition, 2011
    - Group Photo, Some Past Presidents of Division 45 of APA, 2011
    - Carolyn Barcus Award NMCS, Photograph, 2011
    - Gerald Mohatt Memorial Award, Photograph, 2011
    - INPsych Program Grants Authorization, 2011
    - Iva Greywolf Message, 2011